hi welcome back to polar ice creamery
i'm nick and today's ice cream is a bit
of a savory twist there's a couple of
companies out there that have done
something along these lines so i thought
it'd be time to try and see how
we do it but
what is it it's chicken and waffle it's
a big thing in america it's not a big
thing in england although it's really
nice we tried some last year maybe the
year before and it was surprisingly good
i think you need good chicken and you
also need good waffles but the waffles
are
however you like to pronounce it some
people say liege waffles some people say
liege waffles they're sugar bottles
essentially
i've got some here
these kind of things
and
they're
a little bit crispy
much smaller in size
but they're
incredibly good
normally you would have a waffle like
that with a scoop of ice cream or
something along those lines on you know
some kind of
or jam on top but
america switched it up or the u.s
switched it up and
dumped chicken on there and then maple
syrup on top
it's all good what's not to like waffles
good chicken good maple syrup good
anyway made by marcus their take on this
flavor is as follows
we add chicken bouillon into the base of
this ice cream along with rosemary sage
and thyme along with chocolate covered
waffle crunch
it sounds great
they've obviously gone with the herbs
kind of side i'm english should i say
herbs
and then
when you go to salt and straw they've
gone for a cinnamon and honey fried
chicken ice cream this is part of their
picnic series they are known for doing
some unusual flavors we've done a couple
in the past we're going to do some more
next year as well
but it's
croissants torn into bits and deep fried
in chicken fat until crispy
and then added into a salted vanilla ice
cream
but they also say a shaker very special
and in brackets very secret spices adds
a sweet heat
kick
i mean it says cinnamon but you know i
don't know what that spice mix is
so with that in mind we decided to have
a go ourselves the three main elements
for chicken and waffles as
the ice cream scoop bubbles around on
the side are waffles
chicken
and then some kind of
topping to it
we're going to go with maple syrup
so if you want to see how we deal with
those three elements stick around and
we'll show you
so the first thing we're going to deal
with is the ice cream base itself now
what we're going to do is we're going to
make a maple syrup ice cream and for
that we're going to start with our milk
straight in the pan now we've decided to
not use sucrose in here we're using
dextrose
and that's because i want a nice scoop
to this i don't want it hard at all then
we're going to take some light brown
sugar which has got our usual stabilizer
mix in it which is a little bit of a mix
of guar gum and locust bean gum you mix
it into the sugars beforehand so you
make sure it doesn't clump as it goes
into your liquid
then once that's all mixed and combined
add in your maple syrup and slowly bring
it up to temperature now there's no
there's no eggs in this recipe so you
don't have to bring it up to any
particular temperature you're just
trying to dissolve the sugars nicely so
you can actually add the skimmed milk
powder and it dissolves well in your ice
cream base
once that's all nicely combined take it
off the heat and put it in your
container finally adding in your double
cream as we like to do here on this
channel
once that's mixed in
one final stir and put it in the fridge
for a few hours
now we're going to move on to the waffle
part first thing you're going to do is
chop up your waffles into nice little
cube shapes or whatever size pieces you
want and melt your chicken fat in a
frying pan we're going to put a fair bit
in here the starch you actually want the
fat to be soaked into your waffle pieces
now as they start to soak it up you
might want to add a little bit more fat
what we're going to do here now after
it's been going for a good five minutes
and i've made a nice little mess we've
drained off the fat here and we're going
to just cook them for another minute or
so to crisp up these cubes really nicely
the final step is to sprinkle a small
amount of sugar over the top
toss them in the frying pan for 30
seconds or so
take them off the heat and put them in a
container to cool down completely
and the final stage here is to put your
ice cream in your machine as normal get
it churning and the last few minutes of
the churn add in your chicken fried
waffle pieces get them nicely combined
make sure that ice cream is at the right
temperature and consistency and then
take it out and tub it up
[Music]
here we go the chicken schmaltz
it is literally just a jar of chicken
fat there is nothing else in there
it's
slow rendered genuine chicken schmaltz
and the waffles put two together let's
get some scooped up and see what it
turned out like
[Music]
chicken and waffle ice cream
i can smell the maple syrup
i like a strong maple flavor ice cream
but some are a little bit weak in flavor
but
you know you do have to be careful when
using maple syrup and ice cream it's
obviously the sugar content has a lot to
do with it but also some maple syrups
taste
strong some are weak
maple
type
syrup tastes disgusting so if you can't
get real maple syrup maybe just try a
different flavor altogether
but let's see what this
tastes like there's the
the waffle pieces have still got a good
crunch to them because i could feel it
when i was scooping so let's see what it
actually tastes like
[Music]
really nice smooth creamy maple syrup
flavor ice cream
great consistency
really nice scoop to it i mean it's kept
in our cold freezer so it's
you know without that sugar it would go
really really hard
but
the waffle
cooked in that chicken fat isn't an
instant chicken punch
which is what we wanted you know we
wanted a bit more of a subtle chicken
element to it a little bit of a
background flavor
and by tossing it in that bit of sugar
as well it still gives you that nice
kind of bite sweet element so you get
like a sweet chicken
waffle bites throughout
and it goes really really well with the
with the sweet ice cream
i'm i'm not a huge fan of the sweet
cream
ice creams i just think they're too
plain for me and if you've seen the ice
creams that we make here you know we
don't really do plain flavored ice
creams we like to do
big extravagant kind of ones and this is
no different
it's
in england anyway it's an expensive ice
cream to make because the chicken fat is
really difficult to get hold of
but
you know maple syrup
there's lots of different syrups
available
some are better than others some you
know really expensive some are quite
cheap so just use what you have
available
any kind of
savoury element so you know you could
have your your duck you could do a duck
and orange combo
maybe
maybe that's worth a try
goose fat over here we we really don't
eat
goose that often
we use it for our roast potatoes on our
dinners or a lot of people do that and
duck fat but there's no reason you can't
use chicken fat as well so if you're
gonna make this and you're going to buy
the chicken schmaltz i'll put a link in
the description below where we got it
from here
but
you can use it in your everyday cooking
as well it's a great flavor really nice
one to try hope you enjoyed this as a
bit of an unusual savory elements to our
ice cream
everybody on youtube that makes food is
doing ice cream at the moment because
it's summer so if you want to look at
no churn ice cream or
you know
slightly more traditional ice creams you
know there's a lot out there at the
moment but if you like the more
professional approach to ice cream
creating ice cream in high quality
machinery that matches that that you're
buying the shops this is the channel to
watch we will help you create any ice
cream you can buy in the shops yourself
with any ingredient that you can find in
your supermarkets or around your area so
let us know if there's a flavor you want
us to make we'll do our best to
accommodate thanks very much for
watching don't forget to like and
subscribe and we'll see you next time
[Music]